Finding Aid for the Devereux Lake Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Devereux Lake Collection
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0246
1.26 linear feet
Biographical Sketch
1876 Born, Mobile, Alabama
1892 Entered Vanderbilt University
1896 Graduated from Vanderbilt University
1920 Began work for Sandusky Foundry and Machine Company, Sandusky, Ohio.
1935 Became president of Sandusky Foundry and Machine Company
1943 Retired
Oct. 30, 1964 Died in Pasadena, California
- DESCRIPTION OF SERIES
  - Correspondence-Outgoing. January 8, 1935-Oct. 7, 1964. 48 letters chronologically arranged by days and months. Letters are mostly typescript carbon copies and holographic. A fragmentary letter is found last (i.e., page 2, no date, no signature), and two holograph undated notes. (Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-Incoming. 100 letters, alphabetically arranged. Letters are typescript, carbon copies, and holographic. (Folder 1)
  - Notes Kept by Devereux Lake. Approximately 100 pages of holographic notes on various subjects, most of which relate to Vanderbilt University. Included are notes on Chancellors Kirkland, Branscomb, and Garland, on the fraternity problem, and on the class of ’96. (Folder 1)
  - Newspaper and Magazine Clippings. Material includes about 50 clippings dealing with Vanderbilt University, Alumni, and the Vanderbilt family along with information about old homes. (Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Publications. Twelve, seven of which relate to Vanderbilt University. Alphabetically arranged by title: An Adventure in Alumni Relations, by F. Hill Turner; The Confederate Pageant; The Elms; French Military Adventures in Alabama 1818-1828 by T. W. Martin; Facts About Vanderbilt University; The Honor Roll of the Living Endowment, Vanderbilt University, 1947-1948; Mobile; James Hampton Kirkland; Twin Oaks; V.U. 75, 1875-1950; Vanderbilt Alumnus; The vandy Phi. (Folder 1)
  - The Class of ’96. There are approxirnately 50 photographs of class members: 2 issues of the Cornet (1895, 1896): a scrapbook: a pamphlet titled “After Forty Years”; lists of class members: magazine clippings relating to the class: one ’96 graduation invitation; one invitation to a reunion dinner, 1930; list of mementos of the class of ’96. (Folder 2-3)
  - Early History of Vanderbilt University. Material consists of typescript memos and research notes on the early history and founding of Vanderbilt University. There is a considerable amount of information on Frank Crawford(Mrs. Cornelius Vanderbilt). Also included is a description of Vanderbilt University written by Stella Scott Vaughn. (Folder 3)
  - Statements, Reports, and Minutes. Materials all relate to Vanderbilt University, and are alphabetically arranged by title: Addendum to the Chancellor’s Report to the Board of Trust of Vanderbilt University,’ Oct. 7, 1960; Agenda for meeting of Board of Trust - Oct. 5, 1963; May 15-16, 1964. Report to Chancellor of Board of Trust: Digest of the Minutes Board of Trust, May 15-16, 1959; A statement by Chancellor Harvie Branscomb before the officers and Nashville members of the Board of Directors of the Alumni Association. April 29, 1959; A Statement to the Faculty of Vanderbilt University, June 13, 1960; Vanderbilt University Report and Recommendations on Fraternity - Sorority Policy. (Folder 3)
  - Memorial Resolutions. Six, alphabetically arranged by the name of the deceased: Burch, Lucius Edward; Cullom, Marvin McTyeire; Flexner, Abraham; Goodpasture, Ernest William; Mims, Edwin; Robins, James A.; Underwood, Emory Marvin. (Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous. 21 items: an invitation to the 1956 Reunion and Commencement, V.U.; pamphlet, 11 Inauguration of Bennett Harvie (Folder 3)
  - Branscomb as Fourth Chancellor of v.u., 1947; I book cover; I Vanderbilt University pennant; I black satin bag; 1893 Comet; 3-page list of authors and books typed; 9 small photographs of group outing; page 24 of unknown issue of Comet?; I photograph dated 1946 of large group, V.U.; I invitation to installation of Chancellor Heard; “Romance of a Brown Colored Gander with a Broken Wing” - 4 pp. holograph; pp. 17-30 and XXIV of untitled typed MS; I large photograph of senior alumni at Reunion dinner, 1956 - Devereux Lake among them. (Folder 3)
  - Addendum
    - I Remember; Recollections of Childhood and Family Life in the Lake Home on Jackson Street and at Melrose Farm, Mobile, Alabama, 1873-1893, by Devereux Lake. lv. 84 pages, typescript and mimeo. (Folder 1)
Index of Incoming Correspondents
This is a name index of the correspondents of Devereux Lake. The figure (or figures) in parentheses immediately following each name denotes the total number of letters from that person in the collection; the dates are for the time of the letters. The full name of the writer is given whenever possible. The last number given refers to the box in which the correspondence may be found.
A
Allen, Helen, (1); Oct. 2, 1959; 1
Atkinson, Rosa G., (1); Dec. 3, 1956; 1
B
Barbee, John T., (1); (n.d.); 1
Beach, Leonard B., (1); Sept. 1, 1959; 1
Branscomb, Harvie, (10); Feb. 12, 1952, Feb. 12, 1952, Feb. 13, 1953, Mar. 25, 1953, Jan. 17, 1957, Oct, 13, 1959, Oct. 26, 1959, Nov. 30, 1959, June 14, 1960, June 22, 1960; 1
Burch, Lucius Edward (family of), (1); Nov. 5, 1959; 1
C
Campbell, John Neal, (1); Apr. 28, 1959; 1
Carmichael, O.C., (1); Aug. 18, 1939; 1
Catton, J.T., (1); Apr. 12, 1949; 1
Chaffin, Nora C., (1); Sept. 6, 1956; 1
Cook, Charles W., (1); Nov. 2, 1959; 1
Crawford, Everett L., (3); Nov. 16, 1938, May 4, 1939, May 8, 1939; 1
G
Gardner, Edwin S., (2); Sept. 21, 1956, Oct. 9, 1956; 1
J
Jungerman, Ernest W.H., (1); Apr. 29, 1956; 1
K
Kirkland, J.H., (1); Nov. 12, 1934; 1
L
Lanier, Sartain, (1); Oct. 15, 1958; 1
M
McGill, Lizzie, (1); Nov. 12., 1958; 1
Mims, Edwin, (1); Apr. 5, 1956; 1
Morschheimer, Henry, (1); Oct. 20, 1958; 1
Murphey, Josephine, (1); Oct. 28, 1960; 1
Myatt, S.A., (1); Oct. 20, 1946; 1
Ogilvie, Clarence C., (3); Mar. 31, 1949, July 26, 1951, Apr. 30, 1956; 1
P
Pharr, Henry N., (1); Apr. 26, 1956; 1
Phillips, Grace, (1); May 3, 1956; 1
Priddy, Jean Courtney, (2); Apr. 3, 1956, May 10, 1958; 1
R
Randall, Lillian P., (1); Mar. 17, 1962; 1
Rankin, Edwin M., (1); May 7, 1956; 1
Richardson, Cary J., (2); June 26, 1946, June 28, 1946; 1
Robins, Jim, (2); Aug. 28, 1958, Dec. 30, 1958; 1
S
Shea, Edward J., (1); June 13, 1958; 1
Smith, Elmer R., (1); May 6, 1956; 1
Stahlman, James G., (1); Apr. 30, 1959; 1
Stevenson, E.B., Jr., (2); Jan. 15, 1935, Jan. 8, 1960; 1
T
Talcott, Hooker, (1); Dec. 27, 1951; 1
Talcott, J. Frederick, (3); Jan. 30, 1939, May 3, 1939, Aug. 11, 1939; 1
Tefft, Edward c. (1); Oct. 15, 1958; 1
Tigert, John J., (9); Apr. 29, 1936, Nov. 9, 1939, Sept. 27, 1946, Feb. 8, 1952, June 8, 1952, Mar. 23, 1956, Aug. 9, 1956, Nov. 8, 1956, July 20, (n.d.); 1
Turner, Hill, (2); Mar. 10, 1936, May 6, 1939; 1
V
Vaughn, Stella S., (3); Apr. 13, 1951, Mar. 22, 1960, (n.d): 1
Vaughn, W.J., (1): Feb. 9, 1960: 1
W
Watkins, Cora Lowe, (l): May 2, 1956: 1
Wilson, Albert H., ( 2): Mar. 13, 1939, Aug. 14, 1939; 1
Wise, S.J. (1): Mar. 15, 1949; 1
Y
Young, Bert E., (3); Dec. 19, 1936, Jan. 8, 1940, Dec. 3, 1943; 1